Inventory of the Demokraticheskaia Rossiia records, 1989-1993
Hoover Institution Archives
Demokraticheskaia Rossiia records, 1989-1993
93008
Demokraticheskaia Rossiia (Political party)
11 manuscript boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The records relate to politics in Russia and to the 1991 presidential campaign of Boris Yeltsin. They include minutes of meetings, resolutions, statements, appeals, stenographic records, press reviews, and video recordings.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Marietta Omarovna Chudakova papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Komitety obshchestvennogo samoupravleniia records, Hoover Institution Archives
Michael McFaul collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Respublikanskaia partiia Rossiskoi Federatsii Sankt-Peterburgskaia organizatsiia records, Hoover Institution Archives
Susan Weissman radio broadcast interviews, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
The Demokraticheskaia Rossiia (DR) movement was founded in October 1990, toward the end of the Soviet era, when opposition to the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU), the only party at the time, emerged. It united the anti-communist opposition parties in the USSR: the Sotsial-demokraticheskaia partiia Rossiiskoi Federatsii, Respublikanskaia partiia Rossiiskoi Federatsii, Partiia konstitutsionnykh demokratov, Svobodno-demokraticheskaia partiia Rossii, Rossiiskoe khristianskoe demokraticheskoe dvizhenie, Konstitutsionno-demokraticheskaia partiia, Partiia narodnoi svobody, Partiia svobodnogo truda, and other organizations. In January 1991 Demokraticheskaia partiia Rossii also joined the movement.
The participants supported the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic (RSFSR) president Boris Yeltsin in his struggle against the CPSU leadership and the CPSU General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev.
In June 1991 the Russian Republic held its first presidential election. Boris Yeltsin was elected president of the RSFSR with 57% of the vote, becoming the first popularly elected president.
Yeltsin offered to cooperate with the Baltic republics, which were seeking freedom from the USSR. This contributed to Gorbachev's decision to start negotiations with 15 Soviet republics on enhancing their self government. A draft treaty was scheduled for signing at the end of August 1991. However, on August 19, 1991, eight conservative party and governmental leaders attempted to take control of the country from Gorbachev while he was on vacation. Yeltsin headed the dramatic opposition to the coup and secured Gorbachev's return to Moscow.
After the coup Boris Yeltsin consolidated his own power and led the movement to dissolve the Soviet parliament and outlaw the Communist Party. In the fall of 1991 Yeltsin and other leaders of Soviet republics declared independence for their respective republics. Yeltsin became the head of the post-Soviet Russian Federation.
The DR was one of the most consistent pro-Yeltsin organizations in 1992-1993, although the meetings in support of Yeltsin attracted fewer and fewer participants. This was due to the failure of his ambitious economic reforms known as "shock therapy," which caused inflation and currency devaluation without increasing industrial and agricultural production.
At that time two groups struggled within the DR movement, one favoring a coalition of parties and organizations, and the other, a single organization. As a result, at the end of 1994 many organizations resigned their membership.
Given the absence of a comprehensive program, other than opposition to the CPSU and support of Yeltsin, after the collapse of the Soviet Union and the subsequent dissolution of the CPSU, the split in the DR became unavoidable.
As a result, Demokraticheskii Vybor, a hybrid of social movements and governmental organizations, was created. The remaining segments of the Democraticheskaia Rossiia movement either disappeared from the public scene or became part of the democratic opposition party Yabloko.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records relate to politics in Russia and to the 1991 presidential campaign of Boris Yeltsin. Documents present minutes of meetings, resolutions, statements, appeals, stenographic records, press reviews, and video recordings.
The collection contains data on the formation of the movement, its internal affairs, social functions, organizing activities, and political activities from 1989, when organizations opposing the Communist party united, through 1993, when the movement dissolved.
Included in the collection are pre-union materials from regional and Moscow-based political groups such as appeals, statements, and leaflets calling for a coalition. Other materials document important political events in Russia, such as the Uchreditel'nyi S"ezd (1990), the first presidential election (Boris N. Yeltsin campaign, 1990-1991), and the "avgustovskii putch" (August coup) by the Gosudarstvennyi Komitet po Chrezvychainomu Polozheniiu (GKChP) (19-21 August 1991).
Other events reflected in the documents are the first democratic mayoral election in Moscow in 1991, the military suppression of the resistance in Lithuania and Latvia in 1991, and forums, congresses, conferences, and referendums conducted between 1989 and 1993 that document the development of democracy in Russia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as originally received from Demokraticheskaia Rossiia.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Yeltsin, Boris Nikolayevich, 1931-2007.; Elections--Russia (Federation); Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1985-1991.
Collection Contents
- Chronological file, 1989-1993; 1-11 (Box 1-11)
  - Pervyi s"ezd narodnykh deputatov, Tel'man Kh. Gdlian, undelivered speech, 1989 (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes Gdlian's interview to Sovetskaia molodezh', 20 June 1989
  - Orgkomitet Dvizheniia, meetings, statements, appeals, 1989-1990 (Folder 1: 2-3)
  - Moskovskoe ob"edinenie izbiratelei, 1989-1991 (Folder 1: 4-11)
  - Uchreditel'nyi s"ezd, appeals, lists, and minutes, 20-21 October, 1990 (Folder 1: 12-16, Folder 2: 1-2)
  - Kommissiia po vozrozhdeniiu kul'tury v Rossii, 1990 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Svobodnaia Demokraticheskaia partiia Rossii, 1990 (Folder 2: 4)
    Program
  - Registration, 1990-1991 (Folder 2: 5)
    Includes appeals and leaflets supporting the democratic movement
  - Supporting political clubs and unions, 1990-1991 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Ustav Dvizheniia "Democraticheskaia Rossiia,", 21 October 1990 (Folder 2: 7)
    Edited by II s"ezd in 1991
  - Appeals, statements, and speeches, 1990-1992 (Folder 2: 8-11)
  - Vserossiiskii referendum, 17 March 1991 (Folder 2: 12-13)
  - Plenum Soveta predstavitelei, minutes, 13 April 1991 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Vserossiiskaia Konferentsiia Demokraticheskikh Sil, minutes, 14 April 1991 (Folder 2: 15)
  - "Mir, progress, prava cheloveka," I-yi Mezhdunarodnyi kongress pamiati A.D. Sakharova, Moscow, 21-25 May 1991 (Folder 2: 16)
    Invitations and program
  - Plenum Soveta predstavitelei, 20-21 July 1991 (Folder 2: 17)
  - DR Press, independent informative service, press releases, July-December 1991 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Gosudarstvennyi Komitet po Chrezvychainomu Polozheniiu, (GKChP), "Avgustovskii Putch,", 19-21 August 1991 (Folder 2: 19-21, Folder 3: 1-4)
    Includes decrees, statements, appeals, and press releases
  - Plenum Soveta predstavitelei, stenographic records, 14 September 1991 (Folder 3: 5-6)
  - "Osnovy politicheskogo pliuralizma," National Republican Institute of International Affairs, conference, Moscow, 20-22 September 1991 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Svobodnyi Ural (weekly democratic newspaper) No. 13, Cheliabinsk, October 1991 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Konvertiruemyi listok (informational bulletin) Nos. 44-46, October 1991 (Folder 3: 9)
  - II s"ezd, 9-10 November 1991 (Folder 3: 10-15, Folder 4: 1-11)
    Includes documents of regional organizations, minutes, resolutions, appeals and notes
  - Kongress Demoraticheskikh Sil Respublik i Natsional'no-territorial'nykh Obrazovanii na Territorii RF, 14-15 December 1991 (Folder 4: 12-14)
    Includes stenographic report, notes, lists, and clippings
  - S"ezd storonnikov reform, minutes, 22 December 1991 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Materials related to military suppression of the resistance in Lithuania and Latvia, January 1991 (Folder 5: 1-2)
    Includes appeals, leaflets, resolutions
  - First democratic mayoral election in Moscow, 1991 (Folder 5: 3-4)
  - First Presidential election of the Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic (RSFSR), 1991 (Folder 5: 5-12, Folder 6: 1-6)
    Includes pre-election material
  - Plenumy Soveta Predstavitelei, proposals, minutes, lists and notes, 1991 (Folder 6: 7-11)
  - Koordinatsionnyi Sovet agenda, minutes, and statements, 1991 (Folder 6: 12-15)
  - Krov' dushi, by IUrii Kniazev, poems, Riazan', 1991 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Zakon o svobode informatsii, draft, circa 1991 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Pochti ofitsial'noe zaiavlenie komandy Gaidara, interview with Petr Aven, minister of foreign economic relations for the Russian Federation, circa 1991 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Regional organizations' appeals, statements, minutes, and lists, 1991-1992 (Folder 7: 1-3)
  - Dvizhenie "Demokratisheskaia Rossiia," informational bulletin, June-September 1991 and January-June 1993 (Folder 7: 4)
  - DR-Socio (sociological service), 1991-1992 (Folder 7: 5-6)
  - Zerkalo, journal of Obshchestvennyi komitet rossiiskikh reform, Moscow, February-July 1992 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Ob izbiratel'nom protsesse (Izbiratel'nyi Kodeks), zakon Rossiiskoi Federatsii, draft, 17 March 1992 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Sobranie grazhdan Rossiiskoi Federatsii, 5 April 1992 (Folder 7: 9-10)
  - O vnesenii izmenenii i dopolnenii v zakon RSFSR "O privatizatsii gosudarstvennykh i munitsipal'nykh predpriatii v RSFSR" zakon Rossiiskoi Federatsii, 5 June 1992 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Gosudarstvennaia programma privatizatsii gosudarstvennykh i munitsipal'nykh predpriiatii v Rossiskoi Federatsii na 1992 god, 11 June 1992 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Panorama (informational bulletin) Moscow, no. 3(33), June 1992 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Polozhenie o kommertsializatsii gosudarstvennykh predpriyatii s odnovremennym preobrazovaniem v aktsionernye obshchestva otkytogo tipa, 1 July 1992 (Folder 7: 14)
  - Forum Storonnikov Reform, 4 July 1992 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Plenum soveta predstavitelei, 6-7 July 1992 (Folder 7: 16)
  - DR Press, independent informational service, press releases, July-August 1992 (Folder 7: 17-20, Folder 8: 1-3)
  - Plenumy Soveta predstavitelei, 26 September and 28 November 1992 (Folder 8: 4-9)
  - Forum Storonnikov reform, 29 November 1992 (Folder 8: 10-11)
  - Koordinatsionnyi sovet agenda, minutes, and statements, 1992 (Folder 8: 12-13, Folder 9: 1-4)
  - III S"ezd, minutes, 19-20 December 1992 (Folder 9: 5-7)
  - Reitingi podderzhki deputatami VI S"ezda pravitel'stva reform (special information bulletin), 1992 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Akademiia Deputatskogo Korpusa Rossii (Moscow press review), 1992-1993 (Folder 9: 9-14, Folder 10: 1-4)
  - Koordinatsionnyi sovet agenda, minutes, and statements, January-June 1993 (Folder 10: 5-8)
  - Rabochee soveshchanie predstavitelei demokraticheskikh organizatsii Rossii po podgotovke referenduma 11 aprelia, 6 February 1993 (Folder 10: 9-12)
    Includes stenographic record
  - Plenum Soveta predstavitelei, Nizhnii Novgorod, 27-28 February 1993 (Folder 10: 13-14, Folder 11: 1)
  - Referendum, 25 April 1993 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Plenum Soveta predstavitelei, Moscow, 29-30 May 1993 (Folder 11: 3-5)
  - Rossiiskaia assotsiatsiia privatiziruemykh i chastnykh predpriiatii, 1993 (Folder 11: 6)
- Floppy disks, undated; 11 (Box 11)
  8 3.5" discs unreadable in both PC and Mac computers, attempted 18 May 2010
- Video recordings, 1991-1993; 11 (Box 11)
  9 VHS cassettes
  - First Presidential election of the RSFSR, Boris N. Yeltsin, speeches and meetings, 1991 (Folder 11)
    3 VHS cassettes
  - II S"ezd, parts I and II, 9-10 December 1991 (Folder 11)
    2 VHS cassettes
  - Forum storonnikov reform, 4 July 1992 (Folder 11)
  - III S"ezd, 19-20 December 1992 (Folder 11)
  - Referendum, 25 April 1993 (Folder 11)